ILGWU. Convention publications 5780/193 PUBS
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
ILGWU. Convention publications
1904-1995.
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union.
5780/193 PUBS
4 cubic feet
4 linear feet
Publications.
This collection consists of publications produced for the conventions of the International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union (ILGWU), including Annual Journals, Reports and proceedings, General Executive Board Reports, and Financial and Statistical Reports.
6323462
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183 kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel
Compiled by:
Kheel Staff
Date completed:
March 2011
EAD encoding:
Cheryl Beredo, March 2011
Biographical / Historical
The International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union was founded in New York City in 1900 by mostly Socialist immigrant workers who sought to unite the various crafts in the growing women's garment industry. The union soon reflected changes in the sector and rapidly organized thousands of unskilled and semi-skilled women, mostly Jewish and Italian young immigrants. Exemplifying the "new unionism," the ILGWU led two of the most widespread and best-known industrial strikes of the early Twentieth Century: the shirtwaist makers' strike of 1909 in New York City and the cloak makers' strike of 1910 in Chicago. The union also tried to adapt to the fragmented and unstable nature of the industry. It adopted the "protocol of peace," a system of industrial relations that attempted to ensure stability and limit strikes and production disruption by providing for an arbitration system to resolve disputes.
The ILGWU exemplified the European-style social unionism of its founding members. They pursued bread and butter issues but provided educational opportunities, benefits, and social programs to union members as well. In 1919, the ILGWU became the first American union to negotiate an unemployment compensation fund that was contributed to by its employers. The ILGWU also pioneered in the establishment of an extremely progressive health care program for its members which included not only regional Union Health Centers but also a resort for union workers, known as Unity House. The Union also had an imaginative and pioneering Education Department which not only trained workers in traditional union techniques, but provided courses in citizenship and the English language.
David Dubinsky, an immigrant from Belarus who came to the US in 1911, provided strong leadership that led to unprecedented growth in the union during his presidency from 1932 to 1966. He led the union through successful internal anti-communist struggles, built on the ascendancy of industrial unionism by encouraging the formation of the Committee for Industrial Organization, and helped the union become an important political force in New York City and state politics, and in the national Democratic Party and Liberal Party as well.
In the period following the Second World War, the union suffered a decline in membership as manufacturers avoided unionization and took advantage of less expensive labor by moving shops from the urban centers in the northeast to the south, and later abroad. The ethnic and racial character of the ILGWU also changed as European immigrants were supplanted by Asians, Latin Americans, African- Americans, and immigrants from the Caribbean.
In July 1995 the ILGWU merged with the Amalgamated Clothing and Textile Workers Union (ACTWU) at a joint convention, forming UNITE (Union of Needletrades, Industrial and Textile Employees). At the time the new union had a membership of about 250,000 in the United States, Canada, and Puerto Rico.
Scope and Contents
This collection consists of publications produced for the conventions of the International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union (ILGWU), including Annual Journals, Reports and proceedings, General Executive Board Reports, and Financial and Statistical Reports.
Conditions Governing Access
The ILGWU Records, except for publications and materials produced for publication, are restricted. Materials created prior to twenty years from the current date are open to researchers only with prior written permission from the Director of the Kheel Center; materials created during the past twenty-years are closed; the minutes of the General Executive Board are closed. For more information contact the Kheel Center.
Related Materials
5780. ILGWU Records
5780/072. ILGWU. Constitutions and dues books
5780/080. ILGWU. Convention records
5780/080mf. ILGWU. Convention records. Microfilm
General
"Permanent deposit"
Labor unions--Clothing workers--United States--History.; Labor unions--Clothing workers--New York (State)--New York--History.; Wages--Clothing workers--United States--History.; Wages--Clothing workers--New York (State)--New York--History.; International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union.
6323462
- 5th Convention, 1904. Annual Journal (Box 1, Folder 1)
- 11th Convention, 1912. Report and Proceedings (Box 1, Folder 2)
- 12th Convention, 1914. Report and Proceedings (Box 1, Folder 3)
  Scope and Contents
  2 copies.
- 13th Convention, 1916. Report and Proceedings (Box 1, Folder 4)
  Copy 1
- 13th Convention, 1916. Report and Proceedings (Box 1, Folder 5)
  Copy 2
- 13th Convention, 1916. Report and Proceedings (Box 1, Folder 6)
  Copy 3
- 14th Convention, 1918. Report and Proceedings (Box 1, Folder 7)
- 17th Convention, 1924. Financial Report, 1922-1924 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- 17th Convention, 1924. General Executive Board Report (Box 1, Folder 9)
- 19th Convention, 1928. Financial Report, 1925-1928 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- 20th Convention, 1929. Report and Proceedings (Box 1, Folder 11)
- 21st Convention, 1932. Financial Report, 1929-1932 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- 21st Convention, 1932. Report and Proceedings (Box 1, Folder 13)
- 22nd Convention, 1934. Financial Report, 1932-1934 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- 23rd Convention, 1937. Financial and Statistical Report, 1934-1937 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- 24th Convention, 1940. Report and Records (Box 1, Folder 16)
- 25th Convention, 1944. Financial and Statistical Report, 1940-1944 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- 25th Convention, 1944. Report and Proceedings (Box 1, Folder 18)
- 26th Convention, 1947. Financial and Statistical Report, 1944-1947 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- 26th Convention, 1947. Report and Record (Box 1, Folder 20)
- 27th Convention, 1950. Report and Record and Financial and Statistical Report, 1947-1950 (Box 1, Folder 21)
- 28th Convention, 1953. Report and Record. (Box 1, Folder 22)
- 29th Convention, 1956. Report and Record. (Box 2, Folder 1)
- 30th Convention, 1959. Report and Record. (Box 2, Folder 2)
- 31th Convention, 1962. Report and Record. (Box 2, Folder 3)
- 31th Convention, 1962. Report and Record. (Box 2, Folder 4)
  Copy 2 and 3
- 32nd Convention, 1965. Financial and Statistical Report, 1962-1964 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- 32nd Convention, 1965. Report and Record. (Box 2, Folder 6)
- 33rd Convention, 1968. Financial and Statistical Report, 1965-1967 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- 33rd Convention, 1968. Report and Record. (Box 2, Folder 8)
- 34th Convention, 1971. Financial and Statistical Report, 1968-1970 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- 34th Convention, 1971. Report and Record. (Box 2, Folder 10)
- 35th Convention, 1974. Report and Record. (Box 3, Folder 1)
- 35th Convention, 1974. Report and Record. (Box 3, Folder 2)
- 35th Convention, 1974. Financial and Statistical Report, 1971-1973 (Box 3, Folder 3)
- 35th Convention, 1974. The Northeast Department (Box 3, Folder 4)
- 35th Convention, 1974. Report and Record (Box 3, Folder 5)
- 36th Convention, 1977. Financial and Statistical Report, 1974-1976 (Box 3, Folder 6)
- 36th Convention, 1977. Report and Record (Box 3, Folder 7)
- 37th Convention, 1980. General Executive Board Report (Box 3, Folder 8)
  3 copies.
- 37th Convention, 1980. Report and Record. (Box 3, Folder 9)
- 37th Convention, 1980. Report and Record. (Box 3, Folder 10)
- 37th Convention, 1980. Financial Report, 1977-1979 (Box 3, Folder 11)
- 38th Convention, 1983. Financial and Statistical Report, 1980-1982 (Box 4, Folder 1)
- 38th Convention, 1983. Newsletter (Box 4, Folder 2)
- 38th Triennial Convention, 1983. Report to the Delegates (Box 4, Folder 3)
  2 copies
- 38th Triennial Convention, 1983. Report and Record. (Box 4, Folder 4)
- 39th Convention, 1986. General Executive Board Report (Box 4, Folder 5)
- 40th Convention, 1989. Financial and Statistical Report, 1986-1988 (Box 4, Folder 6)
- 40th Convention, 1989. Report of Proceedings (Box 4, Folder 7)
  4 copies.
- 41st Convention, 1992. Financial and Statistical Report, 1989-1991 (Box 4, Folder 8)
- 41st Convention, 1992. Report of Proceedings (Box 4, Folder 9)
- 41st Convention, 1992. Policy Statements (Box 4, Folder 10)
- 42nd Convention, 1995. Financial and Statistical Report, 1992-1994 (Box 4, Folder 11)
- 42nd Convention, 1995. General Executive Board Report (Box 4, Folder 12)
- 10th Convention, 1910. Report and Proceeedings (Box 4, Folder 13)
- 15th, 16th, 17th, and 18th Conventions, 1920-1925. General Executive Board Reports (Box 4, Folder 14)